<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>project on In Pursuit of Hubris</title>
    <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/categories/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in project on In Pursuit of Hubris</description>
    <image>
      <title>In Pursuit of Hubris</title>
      <url>https://ramsayleung.github.io/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>See this site&#39;s source code [here](https://github.com/ramsayleung/ramsayleung.github.io), licensed under GPLv3 ·</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 16:16:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/categories/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rewind your Github summary</title>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2024/github_summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 16:16:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2024/github_summary/</guid>
      <description>1 Goodbye 2023 As I farewelled to 2023, a year marked by numerous changes and personal evolution, I find myself recollecting the multitude of experiences that unfolded. My 2023 journey was nothing short of fascinating and exciting, prompting me to revisit the year from various angles. After seeing hoards of posts in social media generated by Github Contributions Chart, I thought I could also build an APP to summarize my Github contribution for every year for friends to have fun.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="goodbye-2023"><span class="section-num">1</span> Goodbye 2023</h2>
<p>As I farewelled to 2023, a year marked by numerous changes and personal evolution, I find myself recollecting the multitude of experiences that unfolded. <br/></p>
<p>My 2023 journey was nothing short of fascinating and exciting, prompting me to revisit the year from various angles. <br/></p>
<p>After seeing hoards of posts in social media generated by <a href="https://github.com/sallar/github-contributions-chart">Github Contributions Chart</a>, I thought I could also build an APP to summarize my Github contribution for every year for friends to have fun. <br/></p>
<p>I spent my entire 4-days-new-year vocation to build this app named: <a href="https://github-summary.vercel.app/">Github Summary</a>. <br/></p>
<p>This project led me through a series of first-time experiences: first time to try Tailwind Css framework, first time to use and deploy project on Vercel, first time to build project on nextjs, first time to develop a public project on React(yes, I&rsquo;ve tried to learn React for hundreds of times, but never get a chance to use it in real project), etc. <br/></p>
<h2 id="happy-2024"><span class="section-num">2</span> Happy 2024</h2>
<p>While I hoped I could have completed this project by the close of 2023 to share summaries with friends, life&rsquo;s timeline had other plans. <br/></p>
<p>Now, as we step into 2024, I am thrilled to publish the GitHub Summary. <br/></p>
<p>It&rsquo;s never too late to showcase creative work, and this project is poised to generate insightful summaries not just for the past year but for the adventures that await in 2024. <br/></p>
<p>Wishing everyone a Happy New Year! Feel free to explore <a href="https://github-summary.vercel.app/">GitHub Summary</a>: <a href="https://github-summary.vercel.app/">https://github-summary.vercel.app/</a> <br/></p>
<p><figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/ox-hugo/github_summary.png"/> 
</figure>
 <br/></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
