<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>In Pursuit of Hubris</title>
    <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/</link>
    <description>Recent content on In Pursuit of Hubris</description>
    <image>
      <title>In Pursuit of Hubris</title>
      <url>https://ramsayleung.github.io/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>See this site&#39;s source code [here](https://github.com/ramsayleung/ramsayleung.github.io), licensed under GPLv3 ·</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 10:34:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Topological Sort</title>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2022/topological_sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 10:34:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2022/topological_sorting/</guid>
      <description>1 Definition In computer science, a topological sort or topological ordering of a directed graph is a linear ordering of its vertices such that for every directed edge uv from vertex u to vertx v, u comes before v in the ordering.
It sounds pretty academic, but I am sure you are using topological sort unconsciously every single day.
2 Application Many real world situations can be modeled as a graph with directed edges where some events must occur before others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/about_me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/about_me/</guid>
      <description>About me I&amp;rsquo;m Ramsay, I chase a lot of different things. The slogan of this site is In pursuit of Hubris, since:
There are three great virtues of a programmer; Laziness, Impatience and Hubris &amp;ndash; Larry Wall
The first programming language I learned is `Pascal` in a computer-hobbyist group when I was a middle school student. Back to time before, the only thing I could do with `Pascal` was trying to find the maximum or minimum number among the number array, or just calculate the sum of them, which is of less fun.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Design A Reliable Distributed Timer</title>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2021/how_to_design_a_reliable_distributed_timer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 09:19:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2021/how_to_design_a_reliable_distributed_timer/</guid>
      <description>1 Preface I have been maintained a legacy distributed timer for months for my employer, then some important pay business are leveraging on it, with 1 billion tasks handled every day and 20k tasks added per second at most.
Even though it&amp;rsquo;s old and full of black magic code, but it also also have insighted and well-designed code. Based on this old, running timer, I summarize and extract as this article, and it wont include any running code(perhaps pseudocode, and a lot of figures, as an adage says: A picture is worth a thousand words).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s make everything iterable</title>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2021/iterate_through_pagination_api/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 11:48:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2021/iterate_through_pagination_api/</guid>
      <description>Iterate through pagination in the Rest API
1 Preface About 4 months ago, icewind1991 created an exciting PR that adding Stream/Iterator based versions of methods with paginated results, which makes enpoints in Rspotify more much ergonomic to use, and Mario completed this PR.
In order to know what this PR brought to us, we have to go back to the orignal story, the paginated results in Spotify&amp;rsquo;s Rest API.
2 Orignal Story Taking the artist_albums as example, it gets Spotify catalog information about an artist&amp;rsquo;s albums.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serde Tricks</title>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2020/serde_lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 22:29:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2020/serde_lesson/</guid>
      <description>The lesson learned from refactoring rspotify
1 Preface Recently, I and Mario are working on refactoring rspotify, trying to improve performance, documentation, error-handling, data model and reduce compile time, to make it easier to use. (For those who has never heard about rspotify, it is a Spotify HTTP SDK implemented in Rust).
I am partly focusing on polishing the data model, based on the issue created by Koxiaet.
Since rspotify is API client for Spotify, it has to handle the request and response from Spotify HTTP API.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rspotify has come to async/await</title>
      <link>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2020/async_await_for_rspotify/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 01:27:00 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ramsayleung.github.io/en/post/2020/async_await_for_rspotify/</guid>
      <description>1 Preface Today, I am exited to introduce you the v0.9 release I have been continued to work on it for the past few weeks that adds async/await support now!
2 The road to async/await What is rspotify: &amp;gt; For those who has never heared about rspotify before, rspotify is a Spotify web Api wrapper implemented in Rust.
With async/await&amp;rsquo;s forthcoming stabilization and reqwest adds async/await support now, I think it&amp;rsquo;s time to let rspotify leverage power from async/await.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
